Guide to the William M. (William Matson) Roth Papers, 1914-1973, 1950-1973 (bulk)
Department of Special Collections
William M. (William Matson) Roth Papers,
1914-1973, 1950-1973 (bulk)
Special Collections M0333
Roth, William M. (William Matson), 1916-
10 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of William M. Roth, 1981.
Biographical Note
United States Ambassador, American businessman, negotiator.
Container List
- Appraisal Summary Oil and Gas Properties and Other Assets (Box 1)
  All Divisions - Honolulu Oil Corporation
  Prepared by James A. Lewis Engineering, Inc., Dallas, Texas December 30, 1959
  and same dated March 23, 1959
- Memorandum dated October 10, 1960to Honolulu Oil Corporation (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors enclosing the following:
    - Copy No. 4:
      - General Information (Volume Volume I)
      - Production Statistics (Volume Volume II)
      - Wildcat Acreage as of June 30, 1960(see also Box 3) (Volume Volume III)
      - Natural Gasoline Plants (Volume Volume IV)
      - Industrial Research Laboratories Div. (Volume Volume V)
      - Other Assets as of June 30, 1960 (Volume Volume VI)
      - Joint Venture Contracts with Right of First Refusal Provisions - Sections 1 and 2 (Volume Volume VII)
- Appraisal Summary Oil and Gas Properties and Other Assets (Box 1)
  Prepared by James A. Lewis Engineering, Inc., Dallas, Texas, July 1, 1960 (see also Box 3)
- All-Division Exploration Meetings, January 17, 18 & 19, 1961 (Box 1)
- All-Division Exploration Meetings, January 27, 28 and 29, 1959 (Box 1)
- All-Division Exploration Meetings, January 19, 20 & 21, 1960 (Box 1)
- Honolulu Oil and Standard of California - Effect of Share for Share Exchange - Special Study - Prepared by Standard Oil - April 1958 (Box 2)
- Honolulu Oil Corporation Comparative Charts (graphic comparisons between HOC and Standard of California - prepared by Standard Oil? (probably prepared about April 1958) (Box 1)
- Honolulu Oil Corporation Statistical Data Years 1922-1957inc. (Box 1)
  Prepared by A. W. Peake, February 28, 1958 (two copies)
- Valuation of Honolulu Oil Corporation as of October 1, 1958 (Box 1)
  Prepared by A. W. Peake, dated December 1958
- Prospectus - 110,000 Shares HOC - Prepared by Dean Witter & Co. December 18, 1950 (Box 2)
- Seaboard Oil Company studies - 1957 (Box 1)
- Preliminary Organization Study - Honolulu Oil Corporation August 7, 1958 (Box 2)
- Budgets Jan. 1, 1959-Mar. 1960 (Box 2)
- Budget #65 and Cash Estimate April 1, 1959 to September 30, 1959 (Box 3)
- Budget #68 and Cash Estimate January 1, 1960 to June 30, 1960 (Box 3)
- Budget #69 and Cash Estimate April 1, 1960 to September 30, 1960 (Box 3)
- Budget #70 and Cash Estimate July 1, 1960 to December 31, 1960 (Box 3)
- Budget #71 and Cash Estimate October 1, 1960 to March 31, 1961 (Box 3)
- Budget #72 and Cash Estimate January 1, 1961 to June 30, 1961 (Box 3)
- Budget #73 and Cash Estimate April 1, 1961 to September 30, 1961 (Box 3)
- Budget #74 and Cash Estimate July 1, 1961 to December 31, 1961 (Box 3)
- Budget #75 and Cash Estimate October 1, 1961 to March 31, 1962 (Box 3)
- Complaint by Antitrust Division, Department of Justice (Box 1)
  (filed September 19, 1961)
  - Affidavit of L. A. Cranson, President of Honolulu Oil Corporation in opposition to motion for Preliminary Injunction (draft of 9/27/61)and final document
  - Honolulu Exhibit File - Exhibits to Affidavit of L. A. Cranson, President of Honolulu Oil Corporation in Opposition to Motion for Preliminary Injunction
  - Memorandum of Tidewater Oil Company in Opposition to Plaintiff's Motion for a Preliminary Injunction (October 4, 1961)
  - Affidavit of William B. Bateman, Vice President of the Chase Manhattan Bank, stating unwillingness extend loan commitment beyond October 31, 1961.
  - Memorandum of Honolulu Oil Corporation in Opposition to Motion for Preliminary Injunction
  - Pielsticker Affidavits - President and Director of Indiana Oil Purchasing Company, subsidiary of Standard Oil of Indiana
  - Affidavit of John E. Roth in Opposition to Plaintiff's Motion for a Preliminary Injunction (Senior Vice President and Director of Tidewater) (October 4, 1961)
  - Memorandum of Pan American Petroleum Corporation in Opposition to Plaintiff's Motion for a Temporary Injunction
  - Snyder Affidavit - Vice President - Financial, Treasurer and Director of Pan American Petroleum Corporation
  - Deal Affidavits (William H. Deal) Pan American Petroleum
  - Pan American Petroleum Corporation Exhibit #1
- Various correspondence - sale of Honolulu Oil - 1958-1959 (Box 1)
- Various documents, correspondence, bulletins, Minutes of Sale Committee Meetings, etc., in connection with sale of Honolulu Oil Corporation (1960-1962) (Box 1)
- Various documents in connection with sale Honolulu Oil Corporation (Box 1)
  Including: Plan for Complete Liquidation; Application of Various Antitrust Laws to Contemplated Sale of Assets dated September 26, 1960; proofs of Agreements of Sale and Purchase; documents in connection with tax ruling; etc.
  - WMRoth letter to Internal Revenue
  - WMRoth letter to Justice Dept. (not mailed)
- Agenda - Board of Directors' Meetings (part of 1959, 1960, and 1961) (Box 1)
- Consolidated Balance Sheets (part of 1959, 1960, and 1961) (Box 2)
- Annual and Quarterly Reports (1955-61) (Box 2)
- Management - Stock Option Plan, Consultive Agreements, Studies, etc. (1958-60) (Box 2)
- General Correspondence (incl. stockholders' list 12/4/59) (1959-61) (Box 2)
- February 1962issue Horizon magazine (article covering Honolulu Oil Corporation purchase)
- Historical file (given W. M. Roth by Honolulu Oil at time of liquidation) primarily contains reprints of magazine articles, brokerage house analyses, etc.
- Honolulu Oil Corporation volumes - Sale of Assets - Conformed Copies with Property Descriptions.
  - (Tabs 1 to 33), 1961 (Volume VOL. I)
    unboxed
  - (Tab 34), 1961 (Volume VOL. II)
  - (Tabs 35 to 63), 1961 (Volume VOL. III)
  - (Tabs 64 to 106), 1961 (Volume VOL. IV)
  - (Tabs 107 to 153), 1961 (Volume VOL. V)
  - (Tabs 154 to 256), 1961 (Volume VOL. VI)
- W. M. Roth Black Binder Notes taken during training period with Honolulu Oil Corporation.
- TRANSFERRED FROM MATSON TREASURER'S DEPT.
  - File No. 265 - Honolulu Oil miscellaneous correspondence analysis - 1954 through June 1959.leases, financial statements, newsletters (Box 2)
  - File No. 270 - Honolulu Oil Agenda for Board Meetings - June 1958 through August 1959.
  - File No. 280 - Honolulu Oil Directors Material - January 1957 through September 1959.
  - File No. 285 - Honolulu Oil Monthly Financial Statements - January 1951 through August 1959.
  - File No 275 - Budget
    (See p. 2)
  - Gas contract May 1, 1914 (Box 2)
  - Agendas of Special Meetings of HOC Board of Directors 1962
  - Correspondence 1962
- Ways & Means Committee 1968, 4 binders (Box 4)
  - Hearings; Briefing book; Profiles of Committee Members; NMRoth Statement before Committee
- Kennedy Round Agreement - 1967Confidential, 3 binders
  - Fact Book; Texts of Agreements; Annexes to Memo for Pres.
- Congressional Directory 1967, 1 binders
  Includes confidential voting records on trade.
- Trade Balance 1968, 1 binders
- Notice of Public Hearings, 1963-68, 1 binders
- Trade File, 1969, 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, reports, press releases, clippings, speeches
- Miscellaneous publications, 1 folder
  - 1963-65Trade & economic journals, 13 issues
- Miscellaneous Publications 1960-66, 1969, 11 publications
  - Books, pamphlets, annual reports published by trade associations, such as Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development, Committee for Economic Development, European Committee for Economic and Social Progress, European Free Trade Assocation, Twentieth Century Fund, and United Nations Association.
- Miscellaneous U.S. Government Publications, 1962-1973, 18
  Includes publications from Committee on Trade of the National Citizen's Commission on International Cooperation (1965), Commerce Department (1963), Special Committee on U.S. Trade Relations with East European Countries and the Soviet Union (1965), Office of the Special Representative for Trade Negotiations (1963), and Commission on International Trade and Investment Policy (1971).
  Also includes congressional hearings and reports from the Joint Economic Committee (1970, 1973), Senate Committee on Government Operations (1971, 1972), House Committee on Ways and Means (1973), House Committee on Foreign Affairs (1972), and Trade Expansion Act of 1962.
- GATT Publications 1962, 67, 9 Volumes (Box 6)
  - GATT Publications, Analysis of United States Negotations, 1960-61 Tariff Conference. Volume 1-3. 1962, 4 volumes
  - GATT Publications, Legal Investments Embodying the Results of the 1964-67 Conference. Volumes 1-V. 1967, 5 volumes
- WMR Report to the President - Future United States Foreign Trade Policy, 1969.
  Major recommendations, printed draft, and 8 copies of final printed edition.
- Popular magazines with articles re: Roth May 1967, 5 issues
  - Times, Newsweek, Business Week
- Miscellaneous Publications, 17 items
  Unpublished papers, newsclippings, Congressional bill, trade publications (government and private).
- Photo (Roth & Lyndon Baines Johnson)
- Speeches and Statements re: Trade negotiations, 1963-68, 5 binders (Box 7)
- Testimony, Senate Foreign Relations Committee, Feb. 27, 1967, 1 binder
- Briefing book re: Roth's Appearance before Senate Finance Committee, Mar. 10, 1967, 1 binder
- Newspaper clippings 1966 - Feb. 1968 (Box 9)
- Newspaper clippings 1963 - July 1967 (Box 8)
  - Full issues of papers
- Newspaper clippings March 1968 - 1969 (Box 10)